So all the examples we've seen so far,
那么我们目前看过的所有例子中
all of the elements in the list had the same type.
列表中的所有元素都是同样的数据类型
We had a list where all the elements were strings.
我们有过一个列表所有的元素都是字符串
We had a list where all the elements were numbers.
我们有过一个列表其所有的元素都是数字
There's no restriction on lists, though.
然而 列表中并没有限制数据类型
We can make all of the elements any type we want.
我们可以使所有元素变成任何我们想要的类型
We can mix and match different things in 1 list,
我们可以在一个列表中混合及匹配任何东西
so here's an example.
那么这里有一个例子
We've put some strings and some numbers together in 1 list.
我们在一个列表中放了一些字符串及一些数字
That's perfectly okay.
那完全没问题
Where it gets even more interesting is we can have a list inside a list.
更有趣的是我们可以在列表中有列表
Now one of the elements of "mixed up" is itself a list,
现在在“混合”的元素中有一个自己是一个列表
and we can have another list inside that.
接着我们可以在其内再有一个列表
Here we've defined a new variable, mixed up.
这里我们已经定义了一个新变量 mixed_up
It contains a string, a number, a string, a number,
它包含着一个字符串 一个数字 一个字符串 一个数字
and then a list.
接着是一个列表
The fifth element is itself a list that contains
第五个元素自己是一个列表包含着
a number, a number, and contains another list.
一个数字 一个数字 和另一个列表
This example shows the versatility of lists,
这个例子显露出列表的多样性
that we can put anything we want in them.
以至于我们可以在它们中放任何我们想要的东西
It doesn't seem particularly useful
它看上去似乎并不太有用
because there's no structure to the things we've put in the list.
因为我们放在列表中的东西并没有什么结构性
So let's try another example that may give a better idea
所以让我们试一下另一个例子可能会对 为什么
of why it's so useful to be able to have lists inside lists.
在列表中能够存在列表是很有用的 有更好的理解
Before we defined the variable "beatles" as a list of 4 strings,
在我们定义变量 beastles 为一个有四个字符串的列表
just the names of the Beatles.
是甲壳虫乐队的名字
Now we've defined the variable beatles as a list of lists
现在我们已经定义了变量 beatles 为多个列表的列表
where each element of the list is a list
列表中的元素为列表
of the name of the person as well as the date when he was born.
包含人名及他的出生日期
We have the first element in our list as John,
我们在我们的列表中的第一个元素是 John
who was born in 1940.
他在1940年出生
Let's see how that works in the Python interpreter.
让我们看看在 Python 的编译器中其是如何实现的
When we start to have long lists, especially lists of lists like this,
当我们开始有长的列表时 尤其是像这样的列表中包含列表
they might not all fit on 1 line.
它们可能不能在同一行中都写出来
It's okay to divide things into 2 lines,
将这些东西分成两行是可以的
but we have to be a little careful where we do the division
但是我们在做这种分割时要小心一点
to make it clear to the Python interpreter
使其易于 Python 编译器的理解
that it's all part of 1 list.
它们都是一个列表的一部分
The place where you want to do the separation is after a comma,
你想要分割的地方是在逗号后
and if you indent things in a way that makes that clear,
然后如果你用一种方式缩进使其清晰易懂
then you can see the structure, that these 2 lines
然后你可以看看这个结构 这两行
are still part of the same list, and it's the closed bracket here
还是同一个列表的一部分 接着这里的闭方括号
that closes the list.
完成这个列表
Now let's try printing that out,
现在让我们尝试将其显示出来
and we see the list containing 4 elements.
然后我们看见包含四个元素的列表
Each element itself is a list containing 2 elements.
每个元素都是一个包含两个元素的列表
We can print just 1 of the elements.
我们可以显示其中一个元素
We'll print the element at position 3,
我们会显示在位置3的元素
which is actually the fourth element of the list.
其实际上是列表的第四个元素
We see that element itself is a pair.
我们看见那个元素是一对
That's a list.
那是一个列表
So if we want to get just the name from that, well,
所以如果我们只是想要从那得到名字
then we need to use index again, so we can use index again
那么我们需要再次用索引 那么我们可以再一次用索引
to get the 0 position element of that list,
来得到列表位置0的元素
and that will give us just the name.
然后那会给我们一个名字
If we used index 1 here,
如果我们用索引1
that will give us the year.
我们会得到年份